So the first thing I want to talk about this
or a very simple, what the textbook calls
value function based methods right, what the
textbook calls value function based methods
these are approaches where I do not know the
Q* right what I am going to try and form a
estimate of the Q*. So how can I do that so
what is Q* the expected payoff right.
So I play each action, I choose each action
say 10 times I can take the average of that
gives me an estimate for Q* right. So we will
denote the estimates by QT. So whenever we
attach a estimate to an action we will be
using the notation Q take this list, so that
you know so we use Q here, and whenever we
esteem we will attach a estimate of the payoffs
to a state we will denote it by V, V stands
for value function okay that is easy to remember
do not ask me what Q stands for.
So one of the problems with the RL is that
because there are so many different influences
that came in right. So you have at least three
different sets of notations that people use
in the literature okay. So you have to swap
back and forth if you are reading papers in
reinforcement learning right, so somebody
will say that the value function is denoted
by J right and Q denotes the cost function
right.
So if they use disjoint set of symbols at
least is easy for us right, but they will
use the same symbol that one body of literature
will call the value function another body
will call that payoff function right which
is essentially corresponds to the reward that
you are getting at every time right. So that
will be denoted by Q, so the all kinds of
confusions are there. So this is one set of
permutations that I am choosing essentially
because it is the one that is adopted in the
Satan Berger book.
In fact people who are reading edition one
right there has been a overall of notation
in addition to right. So to the extent possible
I will try to follow the addition to notation,
but addition one is ingrained in me right,
so I mean, I have been using addition one
notation for god knows, 15 years or something
right.
So suddenly they decided to change the notation
in addition to, so by force of habit I will
slip into addition one notation occasionally
so it is in your well-being to read ahead
so that you can correct me whenever I do that
right. So do not wait for me to teach and
then go and are well do not wait for the quizzes
and then read the book right.
But read ahead and come to class okay. This
will certainly help you significantly in following
the material better right. So I am deliberately
going slow today warming you up okay. But
then there is lot lot of material that we
cover in fact usually I cover the material
in the book in about one and a half months
right in the rest of the time I will be doing
material outside the book that one and a half
months, two months okay.
So the book is big it is at some point I will
switch modes and start going fast. So reading
ahead helps okay, so we are going to have
QT so essentially what you can do is you can
just take whenever I
took action A right the reward I got at that
time and I can just keep adding those up and
divide by the number of times I took action
A that will give me my QT right.
So how will we write this, let us look at
interview some notation so that is a notation
that I will use whenever I want an indicator
function right. So normally what is the notation
that people use for indicator functions I
or ? right, so people typically used ? or
I so I will use one because we use I and ? for
other things later on okay.
So this essentially means that it is one whenever
it is A or it is 0 right, so should I divide
this way okay. So this gives me the average
right great. So once I have this now I have
made an estimate for my Q starts right. Once
I have an estimate for my Q* so how will I
select an action apologies okay. So I use
t on the left hand side so I cannot use T
as the running variable as well okay. So now
I have come to time T, I have this estimates
for my Q*.
So how can I use that for selecting actions
select the maximum right. So I could be what
we call greedy right, so greedy would be I
am going to select right. So I will take that
action that gives me the max it is R max is
the action that gives me the max right, so
I will take that action that gives me the
max and use that as the action to perform
at that time right.
Is there a good choice or alternatively what
does this choice correspond to exploitation
this choice corresponds to exploitation, but
I cannot just exploit right I have to explore
as well, if I cannot come up with an algorithm
that only exploits right. So what do you think
will happen let us say that I pulled an arm
right the first time well I select and actually
and then you get a reward of 1 let us say
right.
So what will happen to my Q it will be one,
what about other Qs well depends on what you
initialize them with the finish line with
0 they will state zero, but I could have initialized
them with the 100 right I could have initialize
them with -100 I do not know whatever it is
initialization with then stay there, but this
one will become one right.
Now if I am doing greedy what will happen
I will do this again let us assume that I
get a 1 again right, and they keep getting
one every time I pull this. So what will happen
is I will never ever sample any of the other
arms right. It could very well be that arm
3 has a reward of 50 right, just because I
happen to pull arm one the first time right,
I will never ever go and pull log 3 even though
it has a much, much higher reward right.
So we do not want to be exploitative completely
so we need to have some kind of a exploration
policy okay. So the simple exploration policy
okay, so I am going to confuse you a little
bit is called ?
greedy nothing to do with this ? okay. So
this ? is completely different okay, it talks
about a solution concept and just because
I have something ? greedy does not mean I
am going to give you some ? pack guarantee
okay. ?
This is a completely different ? in fact it
was named ? greedy before people even started
thinking about bringing all this pack optimality
equations into RL okay. So what is ? greedy
means any guesses sorry, within ? of the function
okay good choice. But I said this has nothing
to do with this ? it is got nothing to this
?, what I do is with probability 1 minus ? I
will be greedy okay, with probability ? I
will just explore okay.
So ? greedy means with 1 minus ? I will choose
probability 1 minus ? probability ? I will
choose which is uniformly from the set of
actions A okay. Si it is one thing which you
should note here is that if I choose uniformly
from a I still have a probability of hitting
that R max A right. So in fact the probability
of me taking this action is 1 minus ? plus
? by n right.
The probability of me exploring is actually
n minus 1 ? by n okay, so this is something
which is just a small thing net picking thing
but just remember that. So the probability
of exploration is not ? because I am picking
uniformly random you could choose to say that
I pick uniformly from a minus this R max action
right does not make a difference, but I am
just pointing out that there is a small difference
just remember that okay.
So ? greedy by far is one of the most popular
exploration is by far the most popular exploration
strategy that people adopt okay, by far the
most popular explorations. There is another
one which ironically I could not find in addition
two of the book which is also rather popular
is called soft max or maybe I flip through
addition to too quickly to notice it, but
so the soft max exploration policy there is
something slightly cleverer okay.
So if you think about the ? greedy what is
it that you would notice is that I have the
best action the best according to my current
estimates right. So when I say, whenever I
say greedy or best it is according to my current
estimate it is not Q* okay, it is according
to capital Q whenever I say greedy is according
to capital Q okay.
So the greedy action gets the bulk of the
probability right, and every other action
as a equal probability of being picked in
exploration correct. Suppose if some actions
are clearly bad right if I figure out some
actions are clearly bad, so I do not want
to be picking them in during exploration,
because I know that they are bad I really
do not want to be picking them during exploration
or at least I want to reduce the probability
of picking them during exploration right.
And if two actions look equally likely to
be good right maybe 0.0001 difference right
some small ? difference between the two actions
in ? greedy what will happen the one that
is that 0.0001 higher will get the highest
probability okay the other one will have the
same probability as the all the other arms
of being picked right.
But then in reality I just want to be able
to compare these two things more closely and
figure out which one is better right, because
the difference is so small I really want to
compare them and figure out which one is better
right. So what people did was they came up
with this soft max idea right where instead
of giving all the probability two one action
right I make the probability of picking the
actions proportional to the estimate current
estimate.
So whatever is the current Q I will make the
probability proportional to the queue right.
So ideally it should be something like, so
this should be the probability with which
the TH step I will pick action A right that
should be the probability right, what is the
problem with
the different orders yeah, different signs
right.
So I mean the things could be also negative
numbers inside you I could even end up with
a negative probability right, if my QT(A)
was -1 then I will end up with that minus
something as the probability of picking the
ration does not make sense right. So to encompass
all kinds of options what do we do exponential
right.
So why is this called soft max because it
is not greedy just not written to you the
one that has the highest Q value all the time,
but if there is a big difference it will return
that value to you most often. I suppose there
are four actions right and action 1 has a
value of say 19, action 2 has a value of 1.2,
action 3 has a value of 0.7, action 4 has
a value of -0.3 right.
So now this will return to you most often
it will return action 1 to you right, so because
that says a significantly higher value okay
that is why it is called soft max right. Sometimes
what people do is they throw in another parameter
called the temperature parameter sometimes
so ß right. So now think about if ß is very,
very high.
So what will happen to your soft max function
everything will get squished down right, so
ß is very, very high. So essentially you
will be behaving at random, uniformly random
right because all the regardless of what the
Q values are right if the ß is very, very
let us say ß is 1 million right and I say
17 and 1.8 no, no it does not make any difference
right, all of them will look close to 0 right.
So essentially I will be picking all actions
uniformly randomly right, this way it is called
temperature. So if you are very, very hot
right so things will move around at random
right and then people typically cool it down
say they make ß smaller and smaller and smaller
so that from a very high temperature where
you are essentially behaving at random regardless
of what the Q values are as you keep cooling
it down it becomes more and more ß.
So if beta becomes closer and closer to 0
what happens it becomes max right as ß goes
to zero this function goes to max is it become
clean. So it gives an additional parameter
for tuning right if you do not trust me you
can note it out right way it is smart enough
to work it out. So this gives you an additional
parameter for tuning how sharp your probability
needs to fall right.
So this is called soft max and so if we think
about ? greedy then writing it in this notation.
So this will be right, so probability AT=
A* will be 1 minus ? plus ? by n where A*
is the greedy action according to the current
estimate right. The probability AT is not
equal to A* or probability AD = A which is
not equal to A* will be ? by n okay, and likewise
here you have this probabilities here okay.
So these are the two rather popular ways of
selecting actions in fact ? greedy and soft
max are also used in the full reinforcement
learning problem right, they are also used
in the full reinforcement learning problem
for selecting or for implementing the exploration
policy right. Now you can convince yourself
that ? will be very simply you can convince
yourselves at ? greedy right. We will give
you asymptotic correctness provided something
but can you convince yourself that it will
give you asymptotic correctness right.
You are always going to be taking all the
actions right so eventually you will converge
to the true to expectations right you will
eventually converge to Q* because you are
taking all the actions all the time right.
So but what is a problem if I keep my ? fixed
at some value let us say I keep ? fixed at
0.1 at 90% of the times I am behaving optimally
10% of the times I choose at random right.
So what will happen I will know the right
Q* after a long time, but I will still be
behaving randomly 10% of the times right what
asymptotic correctness says is eventually
I should be only giving you the behaving according
to the right arm right. So I should be only
doing the right choice eventually to assume
that what should you do, you have to cool
? right, so ? has to keep decreasing.
But then you should not decrease it too fast
if you decrease it too fast then you do not
have the guarantee that you will get the correct
Q* right. So there are ways in which you can
balance this right and so in fact people show
that if ? falls as 1 by T right that is usually
a sufficient rate, but unfortunately that
will actually slow down your convergence tremendously
because it becomes truly an asymptotic convergence
I mean you have one little infinity for you
to get convergence.
So in practice what you can do is you can
cool it in steps it set the high ? right,
run it for a while okay, and then drop into
a little bit, and then run it for a while,
and then drop it a little bit, then run it
for a while, and so on so forth right. So
the figuring out how long the while should
be is a tricky question depends on a variety
of factors but you can do some kind of empirical
estimates for the time being right.
So do we move on from here, so before I go
on to regret optimality one small thing which
I want to talk about right. So here I gave
you a way of estimating the QTs right. So
what do you notice about that
I run an experiment still time T right, and
then when I want to know what QT is I look
back and see how many times I have taken action
A and then I take the average right. So that
essentially means that at time step T I need
to know what are all the actions I picked
earlier and what were all the rewards I got
for those actions right.
So I need to remember this whole history okay.
So is there a more efficient way of doing
it I am sorry, yeah so I can essentially do
this in a kind of doing the run I can do this
running some right. So how do I do that right,
so I want QT(A) right, so it is some numbers
right. So it is intensely QT-1(A) right. So
let me introduce a little bit of a notation
make my little easier okay. So the number
of times have taken action A I will denote
by NA okay, right look at this okay great.
So assuming that I actually took action A
at this time right, so what will happen okay,
you want me to erase and rewrite both the
numerator and the denominator only a denominator,
numerator sign okay and assuming this is fine.
So now I can do this in a incremental fashion
right, so this is NA to NA+1 RT/NA+1 I can
just keep adding this right.
So I do not need to remember all the rewards
all I need to know is how how many times have
taken action A so far and what is the previous
estimate of QT right. If AT was not equal
to A what happens this will vanish this will
vanish the NA will get cancelled just the
same thing okay so no change. I decided this
is a different way we can write this, QT(A)
okay is it fine right, this is N/NA+1.
So I can write it as 1-1/NA+1 right. Now I
can rearrange this quantities and get a better
looking expression right looks good. So this
is the form of a general class of equations
known as stochastic averaging equations and
this really no stochastic that you need to
worry about here but this is called stochastic
averaging equations.
So one way to think about it this I have an
old estimate right and to the old estimate
I add a error term, so what is the error term
this is my target right I should have predicted
the reward is RT right so this is my target
and that is my actual output right, QT - 1
is what I said will be the payoff RT was what
the worthy actual payoff that occurred right.
So RT- QT – 1A is some kind of a error term
right.
Now this is some kind of a step size 1/NA+1
is some kind of a step size. So what I am
doing is I am taking my old estimate and adding
some a times an error right. So many, many
iterative algorithms that we have looked at
even if you have taken ml that some of the
algorithms we looked at in ml right and many
iterative algorithms that we will look at
later in the course will all have this form,
old estimate times I mean plus some a times
an error term right.
So what is the thing that you should note
here why is it called stochastic averaging
rule, what I am really trying to find out,
what my real target is the what is my real
target, the expected value of RT the real
target is not RT right. The real target is
the expected value of RT right, so my actual
error should have been expected value of RT
- QT - 1 right, that would have been my actual
error.
But since I do not know the expected value
of RT so what I am I using here is a some
kind of a measurement of the expected value
right and the unbiased measurement is a sample
drawn from the distribution according to which
you are taking the expectation, when I say
expected value of RT let so RT is a sample
right, and this is I think I am going to take
the average of all these samples that is going
to give me the expected value.
Since they do not know the two expectations
I can operate with these samples right. So
I am going to form the estimate of the target
or estimate of the error right by using a
sample as supposed to using the true expectation
that is why we call these a stochastic averaging
rules. And so this is a very standard form
that will keep seeing again and again in all
the algorithms that we look at right.
So current estimate plus target- current estimate
right, so this is thing. And this particular
choice for my a here 1/NA+1 gives me the the
exact average I mean this is exactly I did
no approximations anywhere this gives me exactly
the same estimate as I would have obtained
by storing all the values and taking the average
at every time okay, great.
So we will stop here today or we can just
do one more thing and then we can move on
to the other things in the next class. So
far we have assumed that your coins are not
changed right, so we are assuming that the
distributions from which the rewards are sampled
or the payoffs or sample is stationary okay
constant has a different meaning stationary,
stationery means it does not change with time
okay.
So if it is, so when they say something does
not change with time what does it mean, it
means the coin does not change with time,
it does not mean it always comes up heads
okay, when you say something is stationary
okay it does not mean that its outcome is
always the same okay. It means that the distribution
from which I am sampling the outcomes is always
the same okay, but sometimes you might have
non stationary problems right.
So it is basically keep tossing the coin the
coin once I starts wearing off a little bit
right, so after a while it might start falling
tails more often than heads or what will happen
if the head wears off, will start falling
heads more often or tails more often. Start
falling heads more often right, because there
will be more metal on the head side, so it
will be heavier so it will tend to come at
the bottom more often.
So if head starts wearing off okay it will
tend to come relatively more frequently on
the top and it used to earlier anyway fine.
So things will start changing our time right
and so what do you do in such cases. So you
need a way and there are technical ways of
handling it I am just giving you a practical
way of handling, you need away to be able
to track the changes overtime right.
So if I am going to use this kind of an update
so what will be the problem after I have pulled
arm say 1000 times write this number will
become very small it will be 1/1000+1 right
it will be 1/1000+1 right. So the impact of
the new samples I am drawing will become smaller
and smaller and smaller right. Suppose I pulled
an arm 1000 times okay 1000 and first time
I pulled on right the impact will be very
very small.
And if you think about it, I am averaging
like a 1000 numbers any individual number
is going to have a very small impact on the
average right, but this is all fine if I am
sampling from a stationary distribution, because
I already done 1000 samples what is the 1000
and first sample going to tell me right.
But if I am drawing from its changing distribution
so the more recent samples are more important
to me than the older samples things are changing
my coin is varying out or time when more recent
samples are more important to me than the
older samples right. So what do I do in such
cases is, but a <1 so you can do a little
bit of expanding out on this and you can convince
yourself that the as time passes by the older
rewards that I get will get exponentially
lesser weight right.
The first time I do this right the new reward
will get in a weight of a right, but second
time I get another reward what will happen
I will get a weight of a2 going in there for
the older reward, the new reward will still
get an a the older reward will get an a2 right.
So like that so I will be paying more and
more attention to the newer rewards right,
and the older rewards will keep getting decay.
And already it was very simple change instead
of having 1/n constant alpha, so making it
a constant a actually allows me to pay more
attention to recent rewards and less attention
to the older rewards right. And depending
on how quickly your rewards are changing you
can tune the value of a right. So problem
with keeping a fixed is what, if it is stationary
that you not converge if it is stationary
you still not converge because you are still
paying attention to the more recent rewards
right.
And we will keep oscillating around the true
reward right, so whenever you get a 1 you
will go up, whenever you get a 0 will come
down up down, up down we keep going like that
right because you are paying more attention
to the recent rewards. But the advantage of
keeping a constant is that if it happens to
be non stationary right, you take it to some
extent there are other more more robust ways
of tracking non-stationary problems but this
is very simple trick that you can use right.
And more often than not we will actually end
up using a constant a in many of the algorithms
that we look at and but whenever we talk about
theoretical convergence will always talk about
a decay right whenever it look at practical
implementations of this algorithms will always
have a constant a right. So the problem is
decaying a is 1/n is again the same thing
which I told you where decaying ? right the
changes will become small very fast right.
So that is always a trade-off that you have
to right.